Paris 1746.
200 monks have been arranged intoa line
each connected by a wire.
At the end of the line,
French scientist Jean-Antoine Nollet
isabout to connect the final monk to a  leyden jar,
a primitive battery that
stored high voltagestatic electricity.
Without warning, he connectsthe battery
and to everyone's surprise
all 200monks are shocked at the exact same time.
As itturned out,
electricity didn't just travelfast
it appeared to be instantaneous.
Thiswas a huge breakthrough.
If electricity couldtravel long distances
at instantaneous speeds,
could it be used to deliver
messages across thecountry,
or perhaps around the world?
This question
started one of the most
innovative periodsin human history
and eventually led to theinternet.
No, not that internet.
In the 1800s,
there were no computers, phones, or even lightbulbs,
but there was an internet.
A worldwideweb of cables crossing oceans
and connectingcountries with instant communication.
Peopledid business, fell in love, and got scammed,
just like today.
But how did we get there?
In theearly 1700s,
long-distance communication was slow.
A messenger on a horse could take up to a day
just to deliver your letter to the next town.
Sending a letter from Europe to America?
Don'texpect a reply for another 6 months.
It hadbeen this way for all of human existence,
but that was about to change.
In 1792,
French inventor Claude Chappe
set up a series oftowers,
each with a mechanical arm on top.
Anoperator would control
the arms from inside thetower,
and by rotating them in different ways,
a total of 92 unique signals could be created.
Afew miles down the line,
the operator in the nexttower
would look through a telescope
and copy thesignal.
This process would continue down the line,
quickly spreading the signal
over several milesin just a matter of seconds.
For each word,
two signals would be sent.
The first would tellthe operator
which page number to look at in thecode book.
The second signal would correspond
to a specific word on that page.
Word by word,
the message would be sent down the line of towers
and at its destination,
each signal would bedecoded
back into the full message.
Chappe’s systemwas a huge success
and officially became known as the telegraph.
His towers started spreading
allacross the country
and even played a huge role inthe French Revolution,
alerting the governmentabout enemy invasions
in a matter of minutes instead of days.
But Chappe’s optical telegraphhad its limits.
Each tower required employees,
making the whole system expensive to run.
Thetowers couldn't work at night or in bad weather,
and they were only really used
by governments tosend very simple messages.
If there was ever to be a truly fast,
long-distance communicationsystem for everyone,
it would have to be electric.
Dozens of attempts had already been made,
but theyall ran into the same problems.
The leyden jars that were being used
only let out a tiny sparkof static electricity
which would struggle totravel more than a few miles.
This was eventuallysolved in 1800
when Allessandro Volta came
up withthe first chemical battery.
This could provide asteady flow of electricity
capable of travelinghundreds of miles down a wire.
Here is an earlyelectrical telegraph that used 26 wires,
one foreach letter of the alphabet.
At the receiver end,
the electric signal would cause
a small metallicball to move,
signaling each letter.
This was astep in the right direction,
but having a wire for each letter
would cost an enormous amount of
money when scaled up to a full-size line.
The keywas figuring out how to send information
with justa single wire.
In towns all over medieval Europe,
church bells had long been
used to spread basicinformation.
To tell the time,
the bell would ring on the hour
with the amount of rings matching
the number of each hour.
Four times for 4:00,
fivetimes for 5:00, and so on.
When someone in thetown died,
the bell would do multiple slow rings,
three times for a man, and twice for a woman.
After that, the bell would do multiple short rings
to mark the age of the person who died.
If allof this information could be conveyed
by simplepatterns of bell rings,
perhaps the same couldbe done
with electric pulses traveling down awire.
Today, we are so used to having
instant newsfrom every corner of the world.
But just becauseit's fast doesn't make it trustworthy.
That's whyI'm happy that
Ground News is sponsoring today'svideo.
Their app and website let you
accessworldwide news sources
so you can compare perspectives,
verify your sources, and ultimately
decide for yourself on the truth.
Check out thisrecent story about Amazon
getting caught shredding
rare books to train their AI model.
Here we cansee the media outlets reporting on the storyand how they frame the story differently.
Onesource points out the irony of Amazon,
the companyfounded to sell books,
now destroying them for AI,
while another just says an AirTag hidden ina book,
revealed a secret from Amazon without
mentioning anything about them destroying books.
Two sources within the same political spectrum,
presenting the story in a completely differentway,
and Ground News helps you
compare them sideby side
so you can see the full picture.
The NobelPeace Center has even recognized it as
a greattool to stay informed and avoid echo chambers.
It's helped me a lot when I'm doing my research,
and I encourage you to check them out.
Subscribeto get 40% off
the Unlimited Access VantagePlan
by scanning this QR code or by going toground.news/primal.
Again, it's ground.news/primalto see the full picture.
In order for the electrictelegraph to become a reality,
scientists had tofigure out
how to turn pulses of electricity
intolines of text.
That's when American painter
Samuel Morse entered the race.
Instead of sendingindividual
signals for each letter of the alphabet,
he had the genius idea of using short
and long bursts of electric signals.
Much like the church bells,
different combinations of thesesignals
could be used to send coded messages.
He came up with a simple
tapping device that when pressed
connected the battery into the circuit,
sending a signal down the wire.
By simply holdingthe button down for longer,
a longer signal wouldbe sent out.
At the receiver end,
the signal wouldturn on an electromagnet,
pulling a small pen ontoa moving piece of paper,
and recording the signalas a series of lines.
Together with his engineerAlfred Vail,
they developed a code assigning eachletter in the alphabet a combination of short and long pulses.
This eventually became what
we knowtoday as Morse code.
Meanwhile, on the other sideof the Atlantic,
English inventors William Cooke
and Charles Wheatstone
were about to make their own
breakthrough with the electric telegraph.
Theirsystem used a set of five needles
that could beturned to the left
or right via the press of abutton.
Each letter was arranged in a diamondpattern,
and by simply moving two of the needles,
any letter could be selected.
Although it requiredmultiple wires,
it had one major advantage.
Unlikethe Morse telegraph, it
didn't require a complexcode book.
The letters were visibly selected eachtime,
and anyone could operate
the machine withouttraining.
Both sides set out to get funding fortheir telegraphs
And after a lot of persuasion,
Cooke and Wheatstone finally got permission
toinstall their telegraph along
a short sectionof railway in England.
It was here that theelectric telegraph
would finally become famous.
On the 1st of January 1845,
John Tawell murderedhis mistress
and escaped by hopping on a train headed for London.
Under normal circumstances,
this would have been a guaranteed
way to outrun the spread of news,
but little did he know aboutthe telegraph.
After some quick thinking,
a police officer sent a description
of the man through thetelegraph
and the police in London
were quickly able to arrest him.
The public finally understood
how powerful the telegraph could be.
And later that year,
the Cooke and Wheatstone telegraph
started being installed all over Britain.
On the other side of the Atlantic,
Morse wasalso finding success,
having demonstrateda 40-mile
transmission from Washington toBaltimore.
Both countries invested heavilyin their telegraphs,
and in just a few years,
thousands of miles had already been installed,
connecting the largest cities together.
The nextstep was obvious.
Join the two sides together.
With the help of American
businessman Cyrus West Field,
the Atlantic Telegraph Company was
set up with the aim to lay a 2,000m long cable
from Newfoundland all the way to Valencia Island,
just off the coast of Ireland.
Both countrieshad mastered
wiring thousands of lines overland,
but making a wire that
could survivethe corrosive water
and curious sea life atthe bottom of the ocean
was a completely differentchallenge.
This was the cable they came up with.
The core was made from
seven strands of copperwire
twisted together and wrapped in
three layersof rubber to keep it insulated.
The cable was thencovered in tarred hemp
and wrapped in iron wires
to give the cable its protection.
No ship couldcarry the whole 2,000 mile cable,
so it was splitinto two sections
and coiled onto enormous barrels
inside two warships.
On the 29th of July 1858,
the two ships met in the middle of the AtlanticOcean,
and the two cables were carefully splicedtogether.
Both ships then headed out in oppositedirections,
slowly letting the cables
drop to thebottom of the ocean.
A few days later, both ships
arrived at their destinations.
They had done it.
For the first time,
North America now had a
directcommunication link to Europe.
Information thatwould have taken weeks
and an arduous journey bysea
could now be sent in just a matter of minutes.
Over the next 15 years
undersea telegraph cablesspread all over the world,
connecting Europe toIndia, Asia,
Australia, and onto South America.
Injust a short period of time,
the world had changedforever
and it was all thanks to the incredible
engineers that learned to harness electricity.